<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>Thomas J. Vandal</title>
    <description>Description</description>
    <link>http://tjvandal.github.com/</link>
    <atom:link href="http://tjvandal.github.com/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <pubDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2018 22:36:26 +0200</pubDate>
    <lastBuildDate>Tue, 17 Jul 2018 22:36:26 +0200</lastBuildDate>
    <generator>Jekyll v3.8.3</generator>
    
      <item>
        <title>Deciding to do an Engineering PhD</title>
        <description>&lt;p&gt;Deciding to begin graduate school was a difficult decision, and one I recall vividly. I already had what most would call a comfortable job and career path that would lead to the “good life”. At the same time, I didn’t really know what a PhD program would entail and what I would gain. After all, at the company I was working for, we were constantly looking for PhDs to work on similar projects as myself (though with more freedom than I). I began asking questions: After 4-6 years of low pay in academia, would I be right back in the same position? Maybe, but is there a problem with that? What will I be working on? And most importantly, how will this challenge me? What skills can I learn to become better at my current job? What opportunities may open up?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Right away I decided to do a future value analysis (I have always been interested in personal finance). I knew that I’d be paid a reasonable stipend during graduate school and wouldn’t have to pay tuition, but I also needed to consider opportunity cost. And the opportunity cost of not working as a data scientist was, and still is, … enough. On top of that there is accruing interest from my undergrad degree. After calculating this value, I quickly texted my girlfriend (now wife) and said, “this PhD should only cost XXXk”. She did not appreciate that :).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Well clearly a PhD doesn’t make sense financially in the short term (and I’d guess long term too).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then I began thinking about how these 4-6 years of graduate school could be spent and what I am trying to get out of it.  How can I take advantage of this expensive opportunity? I knew that there’d be research, a lot of it. I had already been working on cutting edge machine learning software and published a data science paper in a computer science conference. I was excited to do research. My time also needed to be spent on coursework. You’d think someone considering graduate school would like courses, after all that’s how education works all the way through a master’s degree. I found courses to be repulsing. Their incentive structure quickly breaks down if one does not believe getting good grades is a requirement in life. As John Nash put it&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;“classes will dull your mind, destroy the potential for authentic creativity.”&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Similarly put, classes teach homogenous thinking while research requires heterogeneity. As I did in all my previous education, creativity would be prioritized above coursework. After all, at the end of a PhD, nobody will look at your GPA.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The research is the most important part of a PhD. It gives a person time to touch (ideally push) the boundaries of science, to learn to ask important questions about your field and attempt to answer them, to then communicate your results to your peers and scientific community – all while receiving  all important feedback from domain experts. You’ll be able to learn from, and hopefully collaborate with, the best scientists in your field. This all sounded like fun to me, and I thought I could be good at it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The lifestyle of a PhD also seemed pretty great (depending on your advisor). Yes, there’s the time that is spent on coursework. But that is a whole lot better than a 9-to-5. Constant meetings. The majority of my time would be spent on independent research, reading papers, defining problems, and writing code. This time would be as flexible as I needed, and that freedom makes for a great lifestyle. And if I was lucky and put in the effort, I’d be able to travel to conferences around the world. All while working on an area of my choosing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In the end I concluded that a PhD is worth the effort, if and only if, the satisfaction and skill gained doing the research outweighs the opportunity cost. For myself, I felt that this was true. And in the worst case, I could have just ditched the PhD mid-way and went back to a real job.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The independence I gained during graduate school has been more than worth it. I was able to learn how to ask research questions people care about, and then to search for answers to these questions using the scientific method. I began learning how to communicate this work in various forms, from publishing peer-reviewed papers to presenting at conferences. Learning these skills was not easy, but the hard work was well worth it.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;For me, the PhD has turned into a full-time job. That’s something I never would have thought possible. I am proud to say I will be joining NASA as a research scientist at the Ames Research Center in California contracting through the Bay Area Environmental Research Institute. There I will continue researching, learning how to identify larger scale problems and developing my own research plans. I suspect there will be many more late nights of reading papers and writing code but, from my experience getting a PhD, those late nights are worth it.&lt;/p&gt;
</description>
        <pubDate>Sat, 09 Jun 2018 00:00:00 +0200</pubDate>
        <link>http://tjvandal.github.com/2018/06/09/deciding-eng.html</link>
        <guid isPermaLink="true">http://tjvandal.github.com/2018/06/09/deciding-eng.html</guid>
        
        <category>phd</category>
        
        
      </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
